Norman Hackman Abrams Papers
Norman Hackman Abrams Papers
1970-2011 [estimate]
Abrams, Norman Hackman.
6 linear ft.
Artwork, game and game design materials, motion picture.
5012525
Biographical History
Norman Hackman Abrams (1926-2011) was an American artist and art teacher.
Abrams attended Syracuse University on the G. I. Bill, graduating in 1952 with a degree in graphic design. He worked as director of both television and print ad campaigns for New York ad agencies for more than ten years. After earning an M.A. in art education from Columbia University, Abrams taught art at every level, from kindergarten to graduate school, including Iowa State University and the University of Kansas. When he retired he returned to Syracuse, where he was a fine artist for 20 years.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Norman Hackman Abrams Papers consists of artwork, games, movies, and miscellaneous.
Artwork is primarily in digital format (CD and DVD, but there is also one portfolio containing prints of various works.
Games contains assorted game and game design material (playing fields, score sheets, instructions, cards, playing pieces, etc.). One game, in its original box, is entitled "Shoot the Moon: A New Space Age Card Game." The bulk of the material, however, stored in several tins, appears to be football- or baseball-related games played with cards, including one called "Pigskin Cardball." It is difficult to say whether more than one game is represented here. Some material is in digital (PDF) format on CDs.
Movies consists of Side Issue, a motion picture by Norman Abrams and Robert Lorr, original score by Martha Folts, production of Iowa State University. The collection contains a 16mm film (possibly the original), and transfers onto DVD.
Miscellaneous contains a VHS tape (not labeled, but possibly a video transfer of Side Issue), and a hard drive whose contents are unknown.
Arrangement of the Collection
Game materials, including CDs and DVDs, have been kept in the various tins in which they were donated, on the assumption that this represents some logical grouping. Other material is physically subdivided by type of media (magnetic media, film, paper) but is listed in logical order in the inventory below.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; New York State; Popular culture; Abrams, Norman Hackman.; Pigskin cardball (Game); Side issue.; Artists -- United States.; Card games -- Design and construction.; Card games -- Equipment and supplies.; Graphic artists -- United States.; Sports in popular culture.; Card games (game sets); DVDs.; Digital art (visual works); DVDs.; Game pieces (game elements); Hard drives.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Digital portions of this collection (CDs, DVDs, etc.) are not currently accessible to researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James Abrams, Bruce Abrams, Suzanne Abrams, and James DeRin, 2017
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Digital Art - Hackman R. Abrams, 09/13/2011; abrams_nh_009; DVD (Box 1)
    1: Abstractions (001-018); 2: Upstate NY series (019-033)
  - Hackman Art (1), abrams_nh_010; content unknown; DVD (Box 1)
  - Hackman Art (2), abrams_nh_011; content unknown; DVD (Box 1)
  - Hackman Art (3), abrams_nh_012; content unknown; DVD (Box 1)
  - Portfolio, prints of various digital artworks (Oversize 3)
- Games
  - Shoot the Moon: A New Space Age Card Game, box containing instructions, game pieces, cards, and score sheets (Oversize 1)
  - [Tin 1] "BRUCE Abrams (son)"
    All items listed below are contained in this tin.
    - Game components, game pieces, cards, etc. for baseball-related game(s) (Oversize 1)
    - Baseball: All Baseball cards, 02/08/2010; abrams_nh_008; contains PDF files; CD (Oversize 1)
    - Baseball: b1) Baseball field 6x8", 01/07/2010; abrams_nh_004; containing PDC format files; CD (Oversize 1)
    - Baseball: b6) Stealing Bases - front & back; b5) Hit & Run - front & back, 01/08/2010; abrams_nh_005; contains PDF files; CD (Oversize 1)
    - Baseball: Baseball rules, 02/02/2010; abrams_nh_006; contains PDF files; CD (Oversize 1)
    - Baseball: Pinch hitting - Team A and B, Green and Red Big for average and below average, 02/02/2010; abrams_nh_007; contains PDF files; CD (Oversize 1)
  - [Tin 2; silver, no markings]
    - Game components, game pieces, cards, and score sheets for baseball-related game(s); name of game uncertain ("Cardball," "Pigskin Cardball" "Grand Slam") (Oversize 2)
  - [Tin 3; white, no markings]
    - "Pigskin Cardball" game components, instructions, game pieces, cards, score sheets, playing field, handwritten notes (Oversize 2)
- Movies
  - Side Issue, motion picture by Norman Abrams and Robert Lorr, original score by Martha Folts, production of Iowa State University
    - Side Issue, 09/08/1971; abrams_nh_013; Film: 16mm
    - [Side Issue] Darin #418180, abrams_nh_002; custom video transfer (No. 478180) made by Industrial Color Labs, Inc.; title obtained by viewing video; DVD (Box 1)
    - Side Issue, original can label (photocopy) (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - "Darin, part 2 # 265195", abrams_nh_003; custom video transfer (No. 265195) made by Industrial Color Labs, Inc. (T-30; T-60; T-120); may be a VHS transfer of "Side Issue"; VHS (Box 2)
  - LACIE 2 BACKUP ONLY, abrams_nh_001; LaCie external hard drive, contents unknown; Hard drive (Box 2)